Guide to the Bernard Bloch Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bernard Bloch papers
1936-1965
MS 1129
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
14
(33 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, reports, and printed material relating to Bernard Bloch's editorship of Language, his directorship of Japanese training programs at Yale during World War II, and other professional activities.
Bloch, Bernard, 1907-1965
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. General Files, 1936-1965. II. Japanese Language Programs, 1943-1956.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain correspondence, reports, and printed material relating to Bernard Bloch's editorship of Language, the journal of the Linguistic Society of America, his directorship of Japanese language training programs at Yale during World War II, and other professional activities. The fourteen linear feet of papers are arranged in two series.
Series I: GENERAL FILES consists of alphabetically arranged correspondence and topical files, the bulk of which pertains to Bloch's editorship of Language. Approximately one-quarter of the material relates to Bloch's literary productions, teaching activities and involvement in professional organizations. Correspondents include Frank Edgerton, Edgar H. Sturtevant, and George Trager. For the most part, the files have retained their original order and titles.
Series II: JAPANESE LANGUAGE PROGRAMS contains personnel applications, correspondence, and reports relating to the Japanese language component of the Army Specialized Training Program and the Civil Affairs Training Program at Yale. Particularly noteworthy are the applications and correspondence relating to the Japanese and Japanese-American language tutors.
Biographical / Historical
Bernard Bloch (1907-1965) received the B.A. in English (1928) and the M.A. in Comparative Literature (1929) from the University of Kansas, and the Ph.D. in English and General Linguistics (1935) from Brown University. He was awarded the M.A. (honorary) from Yale University in 1950 and the L.H.D. from Lawrence University in 1963.
Bloch was a field worker (1931-1933), editorial assistant (1933-1935), and assistant editor (1935-1942), on the Linguistic Atlas of New England. He was instructor of English at Mount Holyoke College (1931-1932)., and instructor of English (1937-1938), German (1939), and assistant professor of English (1939-1943), at Brown University. At Yale University Bloch was assistant professor (1943-1945), associate professor (1945-1950), and professor of linguistics (1950-1965). He was chairman of the Department of Indic and Far Eastern Languages and Literatures (1952-1963), and director of graduate studies in linguistics (1952-1965). From 1943-1946 Bloch was the director of the Japanese language program of the American Specialized Training Program and Civil Affairs Training School at Yale. Throughout his teaching career Bloch guest lectured at universities in the United States and at the University of Edinburgh, Scotland.
An active member of the Linguistic Society of America, Bloch edited the society's journal, Language, from 1940-1965, and was president of the society in 1953. He was also active in the American Council of Learned Societies, the American Oriental Society, the American Dialect Society, and the Société de Linguistique de Paris.
Bloch was the co-author of Linguistic Atlas of New England, six volumes (1939-1943), Outline of Linguistic Analysis (1942) and Spoken Japanese (1945), and contributed numerous articles to professional journals.
Language; Japanese language; Linguistics; World War, 1939-1945; Educators; Linguists; Bloch, Bernard, 1907-1965; Linguistic Society of America; Yale University -- Faculty
- GENERAL FILES, 1936-1965; Series I; 13.5 linear feet (32 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material arranged in alphabetical order.
  - A - Az (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1942-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
  - American Dialect Society, 1942-1953 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - B - BI (Box 2, Folder 12-16)
  - Bo - Bu (Box 3, Folder 17-20)
  - Bibliography, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Bolling, George M., 1939-1964 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - C - Cz (Box 4, Folder 24-29)
  - University of California, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Cambridge Congress, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Center for Applied Linguistics, 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - University of Chicago Press, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Comité International Permanent de Linguistes, 1947-1949 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Columbia University, 1952-1960 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Collitz Chair, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Constitution of Linguistics Society of America (LSA), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Cowan, Milton, 1937-1946 (Box 5, Folder 40-45)
  - Cowan, Milton, 1946-1965 (Box 6, Folder 46-48)
  - Cowgill, Warren, 1957-1965 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - D - Dz (Box 6, Folder 50-54)
  - Davenport College, 1958-1962 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Delegates - Appointed, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Department of Linguistics - proposals (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - E - Ez (Box 7, Folder 58-60)
  - Edgerton, Frank, 1938-1964 (Box 7, Folder 61-63)
  - Edinburgh, 1949-1952 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Emeneau, Murray, 1940-1946 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Emeneau, Murray, 1947-1965 (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Exchanges (A - Z) (Box 8, Folder 67-68)
  - Executive Committee, 1959-1961 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - F - Fra (Box 8, Folder 70-74)
  - Fre - Fu (Box 9, Folder 75-76)
  - Ford Foundation, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - Fowler, Murray, 1950-1964 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Fries, Charles C., 1940-1963 (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - Fullbright Act, 1949-1965 (Box 9, Folder 80-82)
  - G - Gam (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Gan - Gw (Box 10, Folder 84-91)
  - Garvin, Paul L., 1945-1965 (Box 10, Folder 92-93)
  - Gedney, William J., 1944-1965 (Box 11, Folder 94)
  - Graves, Mortimer, 1940-1957 (Box 11, Folder 95)
  - H - H1 (Box 11, Folder 96-101)
  - Ho - Hy (Box 12, Folder 102-104)
  - Haas, Mary R., 1939-1965 (Box 12, Folder 105)
  - Hahn, E. Adelaide, 1941-1965 (Box 12, Folder 106-108)
  - Hall, Robert A., 1940-1965 (Box 13, Folder 109-114)
  - Hamp, Eric P., 1949-1965 (Box 13, Folder 115)
  - Harris, Zellig, 1940-1962 (Box 13, Folder 116-118)
  - Haugen, Einar, 1940-1964 (Box 13, Folder 119-120)
  - Hill, Archibald A., 1946-1962 (Box 14, Folder 121-128)
  - Hill, Archibald A., 1962-1965 (Box 15, Folder 129-130)
  - Hockett, Charles F., 1939-1965 (Box 15, Folder 131-133)
  - Hockett, Charles F. (Bulletins), 1951-1961 (Box 15, Folder 134)
  - Hoenigswald, Henry M., 1940-1964 (Box 15, Folder 135)
  - Hoijer, Harry, 1941-1965 (Box 15, Folder 136)
  - Holmes, Urban T., 1939-1962 (Box 15, Folder 137)
  - Hull, Vernam, 1939-1951 (Box 15, Folder 138)
  - Hultzen, Lee S., 1941-1961 (Box 15, Folder 139)
  - I - Iz (Box 16, Folder 140)
  - J - Jz (Box 16, Folder 141-142)
  - Joos, Martin, 1931-1965 (Box 16, Folder 143-145)
  - Jorden, William J., 1943-1962 (Box 16, Folder 146)
  - K - Kz (Box 17, Folder 147-154)
  - Kahane, Heinrich, 1939-1964 (Box 17, Folder 155)
  - Kent, Ronald G., 1936-1939 (Box 17, Folder 156)
  - Kent, Ronald G., 1940-1952 (Box 18, Folder 157-161)
  - Kenyon, John S., 1934-1957 (Box 18, Folder 162)
  - Kepke, John, 1940-1965 (Box 18, Folder 163)
  - Kufner, Herbert L., 1957-1964 (Box 18, Folder 164)
  - Kuhn, Sherman M., 1949-1961 (Box 18, Folder 165)
  - Kurath, Hans, 1931-1963 (Box 18, Folder 166-167)
  - L - Lz (Box 19, Folder 168-172)
  - Lane, George S., 1940-1964 (Box 19, Folder 173)
  - Leeds University, 1954-1955 (Box 19, Folder 174)
  - Lees, Robert B., 1952-1965 (Box 19, Folder 175)
  - Lehmann, Winfred P., 1941-1964 (Box 19, Folder 176)
  - Lenneberg, Eric H., 1951-1964 (Box 19, Folder 177)
  - Leopold, Werner F., 1932-1964 (Box 20, Folder 178)
  - Leslau, Wolf, 1943-1963 (Box 20, Folder 179)
  - Linguistic Institute, 1957-1965 (Box 20, Folder 180)
  - London: 7th International Congress, 1952 (Box 20, Folder 181)
  - Lunatic Fringe, 1929-1964 (Box 20, Folder 182)
  - Lunt, Horace G., 1950-1965 (Box 20, Folder 183)
  - M - McZ (Box 20, Folder 184-190)
  - Me - Mz (Box 21, Folder 191-195)
  - Malkiel, Yakov, 1940-1965 (Box 21, Folder 196-197)
  - Marckwardt, Albert H., 1939-1965 (Box 21, Folder 198)
  - Martin, Samuel E., 1948-1965 (Box 21, Folder 199)
  - McDavid, Raven I., 1937-1965 (Box 21, Folder 200-201)
  - McIntosh, Angus, 1946-1965 (Box 22, Folder 202-203)
  - Messing, Gordon M., 1947-1963 (Box 22, Folder 204)
  - Meetings (LSA), 1940-1965 (Box 22, Folder 205-206)
  - M.I.T., 1960 (Box 22, Folder 207)
  - Modern Language Association, 1954-1962 (Box 22, Folder 208)
  - Moultin, William G., 1941-1964 (Box 22, Folder 209)
  - Na - Nz (Box 22, Folder 210-211)
  - Notices, 1940-1956 (Box 22, Folder 212)
  - 0 - Oz (Box 22, Folder 213)
  - Olmstead, David L., 1950-1965 (Box 22, Folder 214)
  - P - Pz (Box 23, Folder 215-219)
  - Paper, Herbert H., 1950-1965 (Box 23, Folder 220)
  - Penzl, Herbert, 1941-1965 (Box 23, Folder 221)
  - Pike, Kenneth L., 1941-1964 (Box 23, Folder 222)
  - Pittman, Richard S., 1942-1964 (Box 23, Folder 223)
  - Promotion Material, 1939-1957 (Box 24, Folder 224)
  - Publications (Miscellaneous), 1954 (Box 24, Folder 225)
  - Publications (Committee), 1940-1964 (Box 24, Folder 226)
  - Publishers (A-Z) (Box 24, Folder 227-230)
  - Pulgram, Ernst, 1947-1965 (Box 24, Folder 231-232)
  - Q (Box 24, Folder 233)
  - R - Re (Box 24, Folder 234-236)
  - Ri - Rz (Box 25, Folder 237-239)
  - Reading Reform, 1962 (Box 25, Folder 240)
  - Reichardt, Konstantin, 1951-1963 (Box 25, Folder 241)
  - Rogers, Hank, 1964-1965 (Box 25, Folder 242)
  - Russell, William, 1946-1950 (Box 25, Folder 243)
  - S - Sh (Box 25, Folder 244-249)
  - Si - Sz (Box 26, Folder 250-257)
  - Saporta, Sol, 1954-1965 (Box 26, Folder 258)
  - Scherer, Philip, 1940-1964 (Box 26, Folder 259-260)
  - Sebeok, Thomas A., 1941-1965 (Box 27, Folder 261-263)
  - Studies In Linguistics (SIL), 1942-1948 (Box 27, Folder 264)
  - Silver, Henry M., 1949-1952 (Box 27, Folder 265)
  - Simonton, Theodore E., 1951-1962 (Box 27, Folder 266)
  - Smith, Henry, 1942-1965 (Box 27, Folder 267)
  - Société de Linguistique de Paris, 1953-1964 (Box 27, Folder 268)
  - Soviet Scientists Anti-Fascist Committee, 1942 (Box 27, Folder 269)
  - Sperber, Hans, 1940-1958 (Box 27, Folder 270)
  - Spitzer, Leo, 1940-1955 (Box 27, Folder 271)
  - Stein, Jess, 1948-1965 (Box 27, Folder 272)
  - Stockwell, Robert P., 1952-1965 (Box 27, Folder 273)
  - Sturtevant, Edgar H., 1931-1952 (Box 28, Folder 274-277)
  - Swadesh, Morris, 1937-1965 (Box 28, Folder 278-279)
  - T - Tz (Box 28, Folder 280-283)
  - Thompson, Laurence, 1951-1965 (Box 28, Folder 284)
  - Tihany, Leslie C., 1940-1943 (Box 28, Folder 285)
  - Trager, George L., 1937-1965 (Box 29, Folder 286-296)
  - Twaddell, W.F., 1936-1963 (Box 30, Folder 297-298)
  - U - Uz (Box 30, Folder 299)
  - V - Vz (Box 30, Folder 300-301)
  - Voegelin, Carl, 1940-1965 (Box 30, Folder 302-303)
  - W - We (Box 30, Folder 304-305)
  - Wh - Wz (Box 31, Folder 306-308)
  - Washington, University of, 1961-1963 (Box 31, Folder 309)
  - Watkins, Calvert W., 1954-1965 (Box 31, Folder 310)
  - Watkins, Mark H., 1940-1959 (Box 31, Folder 311)
  - Waverly Press, 1939-1954 (Box 31, Folder 312-317)
  - Waverly Press, 1954-1965 (Box 32, Folder 318-320)
  - Waverly Press - Bills, 1955-1965 (Box 32, Folder 321-322)
  - Weinreich, Marcel I., 1949-1965 (Box 32, Folder 323)
  - Welmers, William E., 1946-1963 (Box 32, Folder 324)
  - Whatmough, Joshua, 1928-1960 (Box 32, Folder 325)
  - Winter, Werner, 1950-1965 (Box 32, Folder 326-327)
  - Wise, C.M., 1947-1961 (Box 32, Folder 328)
  - X - Z (Box 32, Folder 329)
  - Yamagiwa, Joseph K., 1938-1963 (Box 32, Folder 330)
- JAPANESE LANGUAGE PROGRAMS, 1943-1956; Series II; 0.5; (1 box)
  This series contains material arranged alphabetically within subject files.
  - General Correspondence A - Z, 1943-1956 (Box 33, Folder 331)
  - Tutor application and appointment forms, 1943-1945 (Box 33, Folder 332)
  - Tutor correspondence A - Z, 1943-1951 (Box 33, Folder 333-337)
  - Student grade reports, 1943, 1946-1947 (Box 33, Folder 338-339)
  - Student recommendations A - Z, 1944-1951 (Box 33, Folder 340)
  - Civil Affairs Training School Curriculum narrative (Box 33, Folder 341)